Ahmed Ali

Pakistan | dev.ahmed.work@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/meet-ahmed-ali | github.com/meetAhmed | +923021084911

Profile

Experienced mobile developer (with over 6 years of experience in Android & iOS development). Adept at problem-solving, debugging, optimizing app performance, and continuously learning new technologies to stay ahead in mobile development. When I am not developing apps, I like to watch sci-fi-based TV shows and play cricket.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Mobile Developer

Modus Create

07/2022 - Present

Remote, Pakistan

- Currently working as a mobile developer at Modus Create, an international organization headquartered in the United States
- Responsible for the development of Alamo Drafthouse Android & iOS App, which has 300K+ downloads.
- Conduct code reviews, write new features, fix bugs, and prepare documentation.
- Implemented MVVM architecture and the coordinator pattern in the app.
- Converted 70% of screens and views to Jetpack Compose and SwiftUI, reducing crashes and improving app performance.
- Wrote Unit Tests to ensure app quality and stability, because of code refactor.
- Implemented Fastlane, which significantly reduces build upload time by 50%.
- Implemented ADA-compliant accessibility features for disabled persons.
- Utilized Firebase Remote config to push new changes to App without releasing it.
- Technologies: Kotlin, XML, Android Jetpack, Compose, Swift, UIKit, SwiftUI, MVVM-clean architecture, Coordinator Pattern.

Mobile Developer

Buzzware Tech Private Limited

01/2021 - 07/2022

Islamabad, Pakistan

- Mobile Team Lead, responsible for managing a team of 3 Android and 2 iOS developers.
- Assigned tasks to the team, conducted code reviews, and prepared solutions, architecture, and design patterns for new features.
- Developed Smart Tracker Android and iOS app from scratch for Vodafone Qatar.
- Added device tracking and smart bulb functionality.
- Implemented live vehicle tracking using SignalR.
- Implemented push notifications, allowing users to keep track of their vehicles.
- Technologies: Kotlin, Android Jetpack, Compose, Swift, SwiftUI, VIPER architecture.

Android & iOS Developer

11/2018 - 12/2020

Fiverr.com

Abbottabad, Pakistan

- Worked with over 40 clients on various small and large-scale Android and iOS projects.
- Created Android version for Flikshop, which has over 50K downloads.
- Created Android version for 'Military Money: Pay & Pension, which has over 10K downloads.
- Updated UI design for Mamazen iOS app, which has over 10K downloads.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Software Engineering Comsats University Islamabad, Pakistan 2016 - 2020

Skills

Languages: Swift, Kotlin, Java

Frameworks & Architectures: UIKit, SwiftUI, Jetpack Compose, MVVM, VIPER, MVC, Clean Architecture, LiveData, Flow, WorkManager, Kotlin Coroutines, RxJava, Retrofit, OkHttp, Hilt, Ktor, Android Jetpack, Cocoa Touch, CoreData, SwiftData, AVFoundation, ARKit, Combine, Swinject, URLSession, Alamofire, Fastlane.

Practices: SOLID, Design Patterns, API Integration, Unit Testing & UI Testing, Concurrency, CI/CD, Git, Agile mindset.

Apps

Alamo Drafthouse Android App

Alamo Drafthouse iOS App

Vodafone Qatar Smart Tracker Android App

Vodafone Qatar Smart Tracker iOS App

Flikshop Android App

Mamazen iOS App

Overboard Solutions iPad App

Personal Projects

Expense Tracker: Github Link (Android)

Expense Tracker is a simple Android app written in Kotlin. I created this project to showcase my skill set in Android Jetpack components (MVVM architecture, Hilt, Navigation components, Coroutines, LiveData, ViewModel, and Room database).

DMerAndroidApp: Github Link (Android)

DMer is a simple Android app written in Kotlin. It fetches categories and images from Firebase and allows users to filter and share them.

Android-VPN-Study: Github Link (Android)

I created this VPN project to understand TCP, UDP packets. Written in Kotlin and Java.

MoviesApp: Github Link (iOS)

MoviesApp is a pet project where I implement new things as I learn, including the latest technologies introduced by Apple. (IMDB Rest API, Aysnc-Await, Actor, Custom Font, SwiftUI, Combine, Dependency injection).